Chris: Coding standards are critical, as when a
developer writes code, they need to make sure that any
other developer in the same team can understand it.
A developer who is not consistent with their
coding items such as naming conventions,
will run into problems later down the line,
especially if they are working as part of a team.
If each developer in a team is writing code in their
own style, then this will certainly cause issues.
The consequences of not following coding standards can
compromise security and code performance issues and
would make it difficult to maintain or update the code.
Leah: Security concerns
If code is inconsistent, contains bugs or
has logical errors, then the software will
be more vulnerable to security attacks.
This is especially the case with complex code [e.g.
not DRY], and errors in the code.
Maintaining ‘Coding standards’ can reduce code
complexity, the number of bugs, and improve the
debugging process as they would help the team
to prevent errors or detect issues earlier.
Chris: Performance issues
Coding standards help reduce the performance
issues of the software that may arise due
to the result of poor coding practices.
So, for example if a program was complex, it could take
longer to execute or perform in the way it was expected.
This would not only have an impact on its
performance, but also on the client or customer
or the end user’s confidence and expectations.
Leah: Difficulty in maintaining or updating the code
If there are no standards and each developer is
following their own style, then this makes it
exceedingly difficult and time-consuming for other
developers within the team to interpret the code.
It is crucial for a coding team to have proper standards
to maintain quality, so any developer in the team can
understand any part of the code that another developer
has written and change or update it independently.
It can help new developers joining the team giving them
clear guidelines and enabling them to fit in more easily.
It would reduce the development cost and time as
the code could be reused and create better team
integration as the code would be consistent.